George Gaylord Simpson Papers 1918-1984 Mss.Ms.Coll.31
American Philosophical Society
George Gaylord Simpson Papers
1918-1984
Mss.Ms.Coll.31
American Philosophical Society
74.5 Linear feet
One of the seminal figures in the emergence of the Modern or Neo-Darwinian Synthesis during the mid-twentieth century, George Gaylord Simpson (1902-1984) helped define the unique contribution made by vertebrate paleontology to the life sciences. A specialist in Mesozoic and early Cenozoic mammals, Simpson's contributions to the fusion of Darwinian natural selection and Mendelian genetics were both empirical and theoretical, culminating in his major works Tempo and Mode in Evolution and The Meaning of Evolution. From his posts at the American Museum of Natural History (1927-1959), Columbia University (1945-1959), Harvard (1959-1967), and the University of Arizona (1967-1984), Simpson became one of the most influential paleontologists of the century, helped in part by his ability to write successfully for both a technical, professional audience and a popular audience. The Simpson Papers include a comprehensive assemblage of professional and personal correspondence, reflecting nealy all phases of Simpson's career. Written with charm, wit, and a sense of literary style, the correspondence touches on all aspects of modern paleontology, providing an important perspective on the emergence of contemporary evolutionary theory, biogeography, systematic theory and methodology, the relationship of science and religion, and creationism, as well as more general issues in scientific epistemology and social and political issues. The collection also includes autobiographical data and writings, lectures, class notes and papers, research data, material on his scientific expeditions (diaries in carbon form, photos, notes, etc.), publication material (he was author of some 800 publications), extensive photographic material, diplomas, and medals.
Simpson, George Gaylord, 1902-1984
Genetics Note
This collection contains materials which relate to the history of genetics.
Arambourg, Camille Correspondence (18 items) 1947-1965
Ayala, Francisco J. Correspondence (27 items) 1968-1981
Barbour, Thomas Correspondence (11 items) 1933, 1940
Beck, William S. Correspondence (6 folders) 1960-1984
Beebe, William Correspondence (4 items) 1941-1944
Bordas, Alejandro F. Correspondence (50 items) 1932-1955
Boucot, Arthur J. Correspondence (2 folders) 1972-1982
Cabrera, Angel Correspondence (32 items) 1931-1954
Cain, Arthur James Correspondence (14 items) 1954-1982
Caspari, Ernst Wilhelm Correspondence (6 items) 1956-1962, 1982
Clark, Wilfred E. LeGros Correspondence (2 folders) 1927-1970
Cloud, Preston E., Jr. Correspondence (3 folders) 1952-1979
Cockerell, Theodore D. A. Correspondence (16 items) 1933-1946
Colbert, Edwin A. Correspondence (2 folders) 1936-1980
Couturier, Marcel Correspondence (34 items) 1950-1973
Crompton, Alfred Walter Correspondence (20 items) 1970-1971
Dobzhansky, Theodosius Correspondence (3 folders) 1941-1974
Dunbar, Carl O. Correspondence (60 items) 1922-1976
Gregory, William King Correspondence (41 items) 1925-1971
Hooijer, Dirk Albert Correspondence (40 items) 1948-1981
Hopwood, Arthur Tindle Correspondence (49 items) 1927-1960
Huxley, Julian Correspondence (3 folders) 1938-1974
Kurten, Bjorn Correspondence (61 items) 1955-1982
Laporte, Leo F. Correspondence (2 folders) 1960-1984
Leakey, Louis Seymour Bazett Correspondence (2 folders) 1958-1981
Lewontin, Richard Charles Correspondence (53 items) 1958-1978
Lillegraven, Jason A. Correspondence (47 items) 1969-1983
Lull, Richard Swann Correspondence (2 folders) 1924-1958
Matthew, William Diller Correspondence (30 items) 1924-1929
Mayr, Ernst Correspondence (4 folders) 1944-1984
McKenna, Malcolm C. Correspondence (4 folders) 1954-1983
Muller, Hermann Joseph Correspondence (25 items) 1957-1966
National Academy of Sciences Records (15 folders) 1941-1983
National Research Council -- Committee on the Common Problems of Genetics, Paleontology, and Evolution Records (10 folders) 1942-1949
Olsen, Stanley John Correspondence (2 folders) 1956-1982
Osborn, Henry Fairfield Correspondence (2 folders) 1925-1935
Pascual, Rosendo Correspondence (2 folders) 1957-1984
Patterson, Bryan Correspondence (5 folders) 1931-1983
Pearl, Raymond Correspondence (23 items) 1933-1940
Riggs, Elmer Samuel Correspondence (62 items) 1925-1941
Romer, Alfred Sherwood Correspondence (3 folders) 1932-1980
Scaglia, Galileo J. Correspondence (79 items) 1955-1981
Schuchert, Charles Correspondence (42 items) 1923-1941
Stebbins, G. Ledyard Correspondence (56 items) 1948-1973
Stirton, Ruben Arthur Correspondence (77 items) 1930-1964
Tieje, Arthus J. Correspondence (30 items) 1922-1941
Wood, Horace Elmer Correspondence (2 folders) 1926-1980
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Subcollection I was presented by Anne Roe Simpson, 1985.
Subcollection II was a gift of Martha Lee Simpson Eastlake, 1975, and Leo Laporte, 1976.
Conservation note
All metal fasteners were removed, and plastic clips were used to keep pages together.
Related Archival Materials note
The APS houses a separate collection of papers of Anne Roe (B R621) relating primarily to research for her book, The Making of a Scientist. Her correspondence with her husband is included in the Simpson Papers.
The originals of Simpson's travel diaries and his original field notebooks are housed at the American Museum of Natural History.
Material on the evolutionary synthesis appears in the papers of Theodosius Dobzhansky (B D65) and in the collection assembled by Ernst Mayr (B M451) to document the Princeton Conference on the Common Problems of Genetics, Paleontology, and Evolution and the Conference on Evolutionary Synthesis sponsored by the American Academy of Arts and Sciences and held in Boston in May and October 1974.
Separated Materials note
All books and medals were removed from the collection for more appropriate storage. Books removed include:
Christian Morgenstern, The Moon Sheep (Insel-Verlag Wiesbaden, 1953)
Harald Stumpke, The Snouters, Form and Life of the Rhinogrades (Chicago: Doubleday & Co.), 2 copies in English, 1 German.
As of April 1989, the medals were not cataloged. A rough inventory is available from the Manuscripts Librarians.
Scope and Contents note
A major resource for the study of vertebrate paleontology in the twentieth century, and a critical resource for understanding the modern evolutionary synthesis, the Simpson Papers offer a comprehensive perspective on the life and work of George Gaylord Simpson. Trained at Yale and employed by the American Museum of Natural History, Columbia, Harvard, and the University of Arizona, Simpson made important empirical and theoretical contributions, helping to define his discipline for a generation of paleontologists.
The Simpson collection includes a comprehensive assemblage of professional correspondence (36 linear feet), with some personal correspondence as well, representing Simpson's varied scientific interests throughout his career. Written with charm, wit, and a sense of literary style, the correspondence touches on all aspects of modern paleontology, providing an important perspective on the emergence of contemporary evolutionary theory, biogeography, systematic theory and methodology, the relationship of science and religion, and creationism, as well as more general issues in scientific epistemology and social and political issues.
Among the notable correspondents are Simpson's fellow collaborators in the Modern Synthesis, Theodosius Dobzhansky, Ernst Mayr, and Julian Huxley, but the collection includes a laundry list of important vertebrate paleontologists, from his dissertation advisor, Richard Swan Lull, to Alfred Sherwood Romer, Bjorn Kurten, William Berryman Scott, Henry Fairfield Osborn, Glenn Jepsen, and to the younger generation of Philip Gingerich, Gareth Nelson, Elwyn Simons, and Joel Cracraft. Reflecting his interdisciplinary approach, Simpson also maintained extensive correspondences with geneticists, ecologists, biogeographers, ethologists, and several other varieties of neontologists. In addition to offering insight into his classic work on the early evolution of mammals and the evolution of equuids, Simpson's correspondence provides a fascinating look into his fieldwork in South America during the 1930s and on the development of paleontology in Argentina and Venezuela. Supplementing the correspondence is the rich material documenting his expeditions to Patagonia (1930-1931, 1933-1934), and Venezuela, 1938-1939. In addition to his fieldnotes and related manuscripts, the collection includes an extensive series of photographs providing key visual documentation.
The details of Simpson's own life and his attitudes toward science are laid out in some detail through his autobiographical writings, but also, in an intellectual sense, through the lengthy series of lectures, class notes and papers, research data, and publications. The carbon copy typescripts of his travel diaries, 1930-1979, are also an important source (his original field notebooks are at the American Museum of Natural History).
Finally, the collection includes a small, but important body of personal correspondence, including his letters home while serving in Army intelligence during the Second World War. A separate, smaller collection of Simpson letters (B Si5) is comprised of letters written by Simpson to his sister, Martha Lee Simpson Eastlake, 1918-1962. Predominantly personal, these recount his travels and experiences on scientific expeditions to New Mexico, Arizona, Argentina, and Chile.
Biographical/Historical note
The vertebrate paleontologist and evolutionary biologist George Gaylord Simpson (1902-1984) was one of the seminal figures in the emergence of the Modern of Neo-Darwinian Synthesis during the mid-twentieth century. Born in Chicago, Illinois, Simpson was raised mostly in Denver, Colorado. Entering the University of Colorado in 1918, Simpson transferred to Yale in 1922, where he received both his B.A. (1923) and doctorate (1926). His dissertation, American Mesozoic Mammalia (1929), was among the first exhaustive analyses of the early evolutionary diversification of mammals, and began what would become a life-long interest in the subject.
During his formative years, Simpson was strongly influenced by his advisor Richard Swan Lull, Charles Schuchert, Carl O. Dunbar, Ross Harrison, L. L. Woodruff, and William Diller Matthew, and from the 1920s, and while he retained a traditional orientation toward field work and collection, Simpson was fluent in neontological approaches. From early in his career, he wrote that he consciously set out to lay "a basis for more theoretical and philosophical considerations of evolution."
After a post-doctoral year at the British Museum of Natural History, Simpson returned to the states in the fall, 1927, to take up a position with the American Museum of Natural History. The Museum proved an ideal spot to continue his work on Mesozoic and early Cenozoic mammals, and supported a series of important collecting expeditions, most notably his expeditions to Patagonia (1930-31, 1933-34) to study Eocene mammals. Out of one of these visits came Simpson's book Attending Marvels (1931), which was the first in a string of highly successful books on evolutionary and natural historical topics that Simpson wrote for a popular audience. In addition, Simpson and his second wife, Anne Roe (a childhood friend whom he married in 1938), co-wrote an unpublished mystery novel, "Trouble in the Tropics," during an unusually rainy season on their expedition to Venezuela in 1938-1939. More importantly, his South American experiences sharpened Simpson's understanding of the role of biogeography in evolutionary process.
In 1942, Simpson interrupted his career at the museum to enlist in the military. As a Captain, then Major, in Army intelligence, Simpson served with American forces in North Africa and western Europe until 1944, when he was forced to resign due to a severe bout of hepatitis. Upon his return home, two bronze stars in tow, he was promoted to chair of the Department of Geology and Paleontology at the American Museum, and accepted a cross appointment as professor of zoology at Columbia University (1945-1959), resuming his work on early mammals, concentrating on the rich Paleocene and Eocene faunas of the San Juan Basin, New Mexico.
The late 1940s, however, were among the most productive years of Simpson's long career. Just prior to his enlistment, he had completed two important works, Tempo and Mode in Evolution (1944) and Principles of Classification and a Classification of Mammals (1945). As a guiding force in the Committee on the Common Problems of Genetics, Paleontology, and Evolution of the National Research Council, he, along with the geneticist Theodosius Dobzhansky, the biologist Ernst Mayr, and a handful of other scientists, crafted a persuasive argument showing the theoretical consistency of Mendelian genetics and Darwinian natural selection. Simpson's Tempo and Mode in Evolution, in particular, was a critical work in catalysing what Julian Huxley called the Modern Synthesis in evolutionary biology, the wedding diachronic data derived from paleontological study of the fossil record with neontological field data, and the empirical data of contemporary genetics. In The Meaning of Evolution (1949) Simpson provided a popular account of modern evolutionary theory -- popular in every sense of the word -- emphasizing the data provided uniquely by the fossil record.
Less successfully, at least in retrospect, Simpson's Evolution and Geography (1953) attempted to provide a coherent overview of paleobiogeography, rejecting the nascent theory of continental drift in favor of more traditional interpretations. Simpson's views on continental drift and biogeography changed radically with the accumulation of new data on sea floor spreading in the 1960s. In 1953, Simpson also completed The Major Features of Evolution, a synthetic overview of evolutionary theory.
An increasing slate of professional commitments provided a full schedule for Simpson during the decade. He traveled around the world with UNESCO in 1951, took part in two conferences on behavior and evolution (1955-1956), and in 1956, traveled to Brazil, where he almost lost his right leg when he was struck by a falling tree. Although his fieldwork was curtailed due to his protracted convalescence and continuing pain in his leg, he remained typically productive, putting out a textbook, Life: An Introduction to Biology in 1957.
Resigning his positions in New York in 1959, Simpson became Alexander Agassiz Professor in the Museum of Comparative Zoology at Harvard University (1959-1967). His later works, both professional and popular, revisited many of the themeshe had elaborated in the previous two decades, touching on systematics ( Principles of Animal Taxonomy, 1961), evolution ( This View of Life, 1964), and paleobiogeography ( The Geography of Evolution, 1965). Anne Roe, a psychologist, simultaneously employed as full professor in the Department of Education.
The Simpsons relocated to Tucson, Arizona, in 1967, when George accepted a professorship in geology at the University of Arizona (1967-1984). He continued to publish until the end of his life, including Penguins (1976), Splendid Isolation (1980), and his autobiography Concession to the Improbable (1978). He died in Tucson on October 6, 1984.
The laurels of an academic life fell abundantly on Simpson. A founder and president of the Society of Vertebrate Paleontology (Pres., 1942) and Society for the Study of Evolution (Pres., 1946), he was president variously of a number of professional organizations, ranging from the American Society of Mammalogists and American Society of Zoologists to the Society of Systematic Zoology. He was, as well, member of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences and the American Association for the Advancement of Science, and was elected to the the American Philosophical Society (1936), the Linnean Society of London, the National Academy of Sciences (1941), and the Royal Society of London (1958). He also received honorary degrees from the University of Colorado, the University of New Mexico, the University of Chicago, Yale University, and York University.
American Humanist Association.; American Society of Mammalogists.; American Society of Zoologists.; Arambourg, C. (Camille), b. 1885; Ayala, Fransisco José, 1934-; Barbour, Thomas, 1884-1946; Bebe, William; Beck, William Samson, 1923-; Bennett, Wendell Clark, 1905-1953; Bordas, Alejandro F.; Boucot, A. J., (Arthur James), 1924-; Cabrera, Angel, 1879-1960; Clark, Wilfrid E. Le Gros, (Wilfrid Edward Le Gros), 1895-1971; Cloud, Preston, 1912-; Cockerell, Theodore D. A., (Theodore Dru Alison), 1866-1948; Colbert, Edwin Harris, 1905-; Columbia University -- Faculty.; Couturier, Marcel A. J., 1897-; Cracraft, Joel; Crompton, Alfred W., 1927-; De Beer, Gavin Rylands, 1899-; De Camp, L. Sprague (Lyon Sprague), 1907-; Dobzhansky, Theodosius Grigorievich, 1900-1975; Dunbar, Carl O., (Carl Owen), 1891-1979; Edinger, Tilly, 1897-; Elias, Maxim K. (Maxim Konradovich), 1889-; Epling, Carl, 1894-; Ford, E. B. (Edmund Briscoe), 1901-; Freeman, Derek; Gazin, Charles Lewis, 1904-; Geological Society of America.; Gingerich, Philip D.; Gould, Stephen Jay; Grant, Verne; Gregory, Joseph Tracy, 1914-; Gregory, William K. (William King), 1876-; Hall, E. Raymond (Eugene Raymond), 1902-; Harvard University--Faculty; Heberer, Gerhardt, 1901-1973; Hibbard, Claude William, 1905-1973; Hoffstetter, Robert; Hooijer, Dirk Albert; Hopwood, Arthur Tindell, 1897-; Huxley, Julian, 1887-1975; International Commission on Zoological Nomenclature; Jenkins, Farish A., 1940-; Jepsen, Glenn Lowell, 1904-; Kellogg, Remington, 1893-; Kermack, K. A. (Kenneth A.); Kuhn-Schnyder, Emil; Kurtén, BjC6rn; Laporte, Léo F.; Lattimore, Owen, 1900-; Lavocat, René; Leakey, L. S. B., (Louis Seymour Bazett), 1903-1972; Lewontin, Richard Charles, 1929-; Lillegraven, Jason A., 1938-; Lull, Richard Swann, 1867-1957; Marshall, Larry G.; Matthew, William Diller, 1871-1930; Mayr, Ernst, 1904-2005; McGrew, Paul Orman, 1909-; McKenna, Malcolm C.; Montagu, Ashley, 1905-1999; Morgan, Arthur Ernest, 1878-1975; Muller, H. J., (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967; National Academy of Sciences. (U.S.); Nelson, Gareth J.; Newell, Norman Dennis, 1909-2005; Olsen, Stanley John, 1919-; Olson, Everett Claire, 1910-; Osborn, Henry Fairfield, 1857-1935; Ostrom, John H.; Pascual, Rosendo; Patterson, Bryan, 1909-; Phelps, William Henry; Reig, Osvaldo; Rensch, Bernhard, 1900-; Reynolds, Thomas Emmett, 1892-; Riggs, Elmer Samuel, 1869-; Roe, Anne, 1904-; Romer, Alfred Sherwood, 1894-1973; Russell, Loris Shano, 1904-; Scaglia, Galileo J.; Schaeffer, Bobb; Schuchert, Charles, 1858-1942; Scott, William Berryman, 1858-1947; Simons, Elwyn L.; Society for the Study of Evolution.; Society of Systematic Zoology (U.S.); Society of Vertebrate Paleontology.; Stebbins, G. Ledyard, (George Ledyard), 1906-2000; Stirtin, Ruben Arthur, 1901-1966; Tieje, Arthur Jerrold, 1889-; University of Arizona--Faculty; Van Valen, Leigh; Westoll, T. Stanley; Wilson, Edward Osborne, 1929-; Wood, Albert Elmer, 1910-; Wood, Horace; Woodward, Arthur Smith, 1864-1944; Behavior evolution; Biogeography.; Biology--Classification; Creationism.; Diplomas.; Evolution; Evolution (Biology); Evolution--Religious aspects; Evolutionary synthesis.; Extinction (Biology); Field notes.; Genetics; Horses--Evolution; Mammals, Fossil; Mammals--Evolution; Medals; Natural selection; Paleontology; Paleontology--Argentina--Patagonia; Paleontology--Venezuela; Patagonia (Argentina and Chile)--Description and travel; Photographs; Photonegatives; Religion and science--20th century; Scientific expeditions; Slides.; Venezuela--Description and travel; World War, 1939-1945
- George Gaylord Simpson Papers
  - Series I. Correspondence, 1925-1984; 36 linear feet (Box 1-73)
    Scope and Contents note
    Approximately 4,600 folders of professional, administrative, and personal letters to and from Simpson. The professional correspondence represents several aspects of Simpson's career. First are his original contributions to technical knowledge in paleontology, geology, zoology, and taxonomy. Second are his involvements with professional organizations, the most prominent being the National Science Foundation, the National Research Council, the Society of Vertebrate Paleontology, the Society for the Study of Evolution, the National Academy of Sciences, and the American Philosophical Society. Third are Simpson's comments and criticisms of his colleague's manuscripts, correspondence, and activities. Fourth are the informal and personal exchanges of news, activities, and gossip between more intimate associates. In the later portion of Simpson's career, correspondence with laypeople increased, and topics discussed include horses, penguins, cosmology, general paleontology, and creationism.
    Administrative correspondence is less plentiful in this series. Information regarding the University of Arizona and the Simroe Foundation are lacking, and Simpson's activities in the American Museum of Natural History are almost entirely absent (although the Library of the American Museum of Natural History possesses related materials). However, Simpson's duties as the Agassiz Professor at the Museum of Comparative Zoology, and the travel arrangements for Simpson's many trips and excursions, are well documented.
    Intermingled with professional and administrative matters are personal comments and details concerning Simpson, his family, and his activities. Simpson occasionally reflected on his own motivations, ambitions, and history in his letters. Additionally, material in this series provides a panorama of personalities that Simpson comments on; from unrestrained frankness to diplomatic courtesy, and from warm humor to perturbed spite.
    Many items deserve note in this series. Most prominent are the detailed letters between Simpson and his major publishers, including Columbia University Press, Yale University Press, and Harcourt, Brace, and World. These exchanges document the process of publication. Correspondence of this type is filed under the name of the publisher. However, in some cases Simpson kept files under the last name of particular editors. Users of this collection should be sure to check both headings when searching in the correspondence.
    In addition, correspondence with collaborators on Life: An Introduction to Biology is especially extensive and rich in detail. As are Simpson's connection with South American paleontologists and geologists, which is demonstrated by the voluminous correspondence with Latin American scientists. Also of note are a group of letters between George and Anne Roe Simpson entitled "Observations during a war," written during Simpson's World War II military service in Europe.
    The material in this series does not represent the complete corpus of known correspondence from Simpson. Administrative activities are documented in manuscripts deposited with the American Museum of Natural History and Harvard University. Field notes and papers relating to Simpson's expeditions are housed at the American Museum of Natural History's Department of Vertebrate Paleontology. The extensive library kept by the Simpsons was dispersed upon his death. Books relating to anthropology, near and far east languages, and genetics were donated to the University of Arizona. The bulk of his collection, which included his entire reprint collection, was donated to the Florida State Museum (Gainesville), under the supervision of Dr. David Webb.